Start Time,End Time,Nastaliq,Devnagri,Roman,Translation,Commentary
0:26,0:48,یہ نہ تھی ہماری قسمت کہ وصالِ یار ہوتا,ये न थी हमारी क़िस्मत कि विसाल-ए यार होता,yih nah thii hamaarii qismat kih visaal-e yaar hotaa,this was not our destiny/fate-- that union with the beloved would take place,"This is not a verse, but an arrow quenched in the poison of vain longing. - Bekhud Mohani"
0:49,1:09,اگر اور جیتے رہتے یہی انتظار ہوتا,अगर और जीते रहते यही इंतिज़ार होता,agar aur jiite rahte yihii intizaar hotaa,"if we had kept on living longer, there would have been this very same waiting ","Since waiting is more painful than death, it's good that we died, and were thus saved from the pain of waiting for union with the beloved. - Baqir"
1:28,1:42,کوئی میرے دل سے پوچھے ترے تیرِ نیم کش کو,कोई मेरे दिल से पूछे तिरे तीर-ए नीम-कश को,koii mere dil se puuchhe tire tiir-e niim-kash ko,let someone ask my heart about your half-drawn arrow,"A 'half-drawn arrow' is one from a bow that at the time of release was not fully pulled tight, and for this reason it wasn't able to go through. - Nazm"
1:45,2:06,یہ خلش کہاں سے ہوتی جو جگر کے پار ہوتا,ये ख़लिश कहाँ से होती जो जिगर के पार होता,yih khalish kahaan se hotii jo jigar ke paar hotaa,"where would this pricking/anxiety have been, if it had [gone through and] been beyond the liver?","The point is that if the arrow of your coquetry (which had veered aside) had been released with full force, then the heart would have been finished off in a moment, and I would not have become acquainted with the relish of the tension and pricking of passion. - Bekhud Mohani"
2:20,2:34,یہ کہاں کی دوستی ہے کہ بنے ہیں دوست ناصح,ये कहाँ की दोस्ती है कि बने हैं दोस्त नासिह,yih kahaan kii dostii hai kih bane hain dost naasih,"what kind of friendship is this, that friends have become Advisors?!","The complaint about the friends is, why have they resolved on giving advice? - Nazm"
2:36,2:58,کوئی چارہ ساز ہوتا کوئی غم گسار ہوتا,कोई चारा-साज़ होता कोई ग़म-गुसार होता,koii chaarah-saaz hotaa koii gham-gusaar hotaa,"if only there had been some helper, if only there had been some sympathizer!","And, of course, 'what kind of friendship is this?' might be more than a rhetorical question, but an actual exploratory one. In which case we could wonder whether one phrase of the second line applies to the friends, and the other to the Advisor, so that two kinds of friendship are envisioned? Or are both phrases applicable to both, since their behavior is equally remote from actual friendship? - Frances Pritchett"
3:18,3:33,کہوں کس سے میں کہ کیا ہے شبِ غم بری بلا ہے,कहूँ किस से मैं कि क्या है शब-ए ग़म बुरी बला है,kahuun kis se main kih kyaa hai shab-e gham burii balaa hai,to whom might/would I say what/how it is-- the night of grief is a bad disaster!,One of the torments of the 'night of grief' is that the lover is so alone-- so there's nobody at hand whom he can tell about it. He only know that it's 'bad news'-- بری بلا has that kind of colloquial energy. - Frances Pritchett
3:35,3:57,مجھے کیا برا تھا مرنا اگر ایک بار ہوتا,मुझे क्या बुरा था मरना अगर एक बार होता,mujhe kyaa buraa thaa marnaa agar ek baar hotaa,"what harm/'bad' to me was dying, if it had taken place one time?","During the night of grief I am compelled to die thousands of times. I endure the suffering of death, and then I don't die. How excellently he has shown that the night of grief surpasses death! - Bekhud Dihlavi"
4:09,4:23,یہ مسائلِ تصوّف یہ ترا بیان غالب,ये मसाइल-ए तसव्वुफ़ ये तिरा बयान ग़ालिब,yih masaail-e tasavvuf yih tiraa bayaan Ghaalib,"these problems of mysticism! this description/expression of yours, Ghalib!","Both these things are among Mirza Sahib's specialties: one, style of speech, and the other, a mood of mysticism. Bekhud Dihlavi"
4:28,4:50,تجھے ہم ولی سمجھتے جو نہ بادہ خوار ہوتا,तुझे हम वली समझते जो न बादा-ख़्वार होता,tujhe ham valii samajhte jo nah baadah-khvaar hotaa,we would consider you a saint-- if you weren't a wine-drinker,"Since the closing-verse must contain the poet's pen-name, it is commonly self-referential or self-addressing. Sometimes, as in this case, it seems to represent words spoken to the poet by others. But rarely does this common device appear to such advantage, so subtly humorous on several levels, as it does in this verse. The observer condescends to the poet, while we condescend to the observer, and both processes amuse and delight us. And who's to say the poet is not condescending to us as well? - Frances Pritchett"
